Guide to the Papers of William Baskerville Hamilton, circa 1700-1975 RL.00495
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
William Baskerville Hamilton papers
1700-1975
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Hamilton, William Baskerville, 1908-1972
RL.00495
80 Linear Feet 53,700 items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Papers of William Baskerville Hamilton were gifts to Duke University, 1965-1975.
Biographical Note
William Baskerville Hamilton was Professor of history, Duke University, Durham, N.C. Biographical and Autobiographical Information is filed in the first box of the collection. It includes a vita, letters, articles, clippings, obituaries, and other items.
Collection Overview
Correspondence, memoranda, and reports, relating to Hamilton's teaching career; reasearch notes for his work in antebellum Mississippi history, particularly the Territorial period, and for biographies of William Wyndham Grenville, Baron, and William Murray, Earl of Mansfield; and personal and family papers. Includes ca. 9,000 British historical manuscripts donated by Hamilton, cataloged separately by the repository. Correspondents include Nash Kerr Burger, Hubert Creekmore, Eudora Welty, and other Mississippi literary figures.
College teachers -- Correspondence; United States -- History -- Study and teaching; Mississippi -- History -- Study and teaching; Great Britain -- History -- Study and teaching; Great Britain -- History -- Sources; North Carolina -- Durham County -- Durham; Grenville, William Wyndham Grenville, Baron, 1759-1834; Mansfield, William Murray, Earl of, 1705-1793; Hamilton, William Baskerville, 1908-1972; Welty, Eudora, 1909-2001; Duke University. Department of History -- Faculty; Creekmore, Hubert, 1907-1966
- Biographical and Autobiographical Information
  Scope and Contents note
  This information is filed in the first box of the collection. It includes a vita, letters, articles, clippings, obituaries, and other items.
- Alphabetical Files
  This series contains files on various individuals, corporations, and publications, arranged in alphabetical order. Additional alphabetical files can be found in boxes 169-176.
  - Adair, Douglass, 1947 (Box 1)
  - Adams, Randolph G., 1940-1942 (Box 1)
  - Addoms, Ruth, 1943 (Box 1)
  - Advisory Committee on Historical Markers, 1949-1952 (Box 1)
  - Aldstadt, David P., 1961-1966 (Box 1)
  - Allen, George Garland, 1960 (Box 1)
  - Altschul, Frank, 1940 (Box 1)
  - American Antiquarian Society, 1939 (Box 2)
  - American Council on Education, 1942 (Box 2)
  - American Council of Learned Societies. Faculty Study Fellowship, 1949-1962 (Box 2)
  - American Historical Association-Pacific Coast Branch, 1962 (Box 2)
  - American Historical Association-Publications Sales, 1963 (Box 2)
  - American Historical Association-see also Littleton-Griswold Fund Committee (box 83) (Box 2)
  - American Peoples Encyclopedia, 1945 (Box 2)
  - Americans United for World Organization, Inc., 1945 (Box 2)
  - Anglo-American Conference of Historians, 1957-1966 (Box 2a)
  - Ansley, Roger (Box 2a)
  - Appleton-Century Co., 1944-1948 (Box 2a)
  - Archer, Dorothy (Box 2a)
  - Archie, William C., 1950-1959 (Box 2a)
  - Archivists Convention, 1948 (Box 2a)
  - Arizona Faculty Organization, 1949 (Box 2a)
  - Army Air Forces, 1942 (Box 2a)
  - Arnold, Noble, 1940 (Box 2a)
  - Artz, Frederick B., 1941-1948 (Box 2a)
  - Ashmore, Frank L. (Box 2a)
  - Askew, William C., 1940-1957 (Box 2a)
  - Aspinall, A. (Box 2a)
  - Association of Research Libraries, 1954 (Box 2a)
  - Association of Universities of the British Commonwealth (Box 2a)
  - Athenaeum, 1942-1962 (Box 2a)
  - Austin, Warren R., 1939 (Box 2a)
  - Ausubel, Herman, 1952 (Box 2a)
  - Axelson, Eric (Box 2a)
  - Bagnell, Sam H., 1940 (Box 3)
  - Bailey, Mrs. Edward, 1934-1946 (Box 3)
  - Bailey, John C., 1941 (Box 3)
  - Bailey, Josiah W., 1939-1946 (Box 3)
  - Baily, (Francis), Journey of a Tour, Alan J. Marks (Box 3)
  - Baldwin, Alice M., 1939-1960 (Box 3)
  - Baldwin, Benjamin R., 1940 (Box 3)
  - Barber, Harold R., 1948-1952 (Box 3)
  - Bargar, Bradley D. (Box 3)
  - Barkley, Alben W., 1941 (Box 3)
  - Barnes, Donald G. (Box 3)
  - Barnes, Walter C., 1941 (Box 3)
  - Barnwell, Robert, 1938 (Box 3)
  - Barrier, Norman Gould (Box 3)
  - Barron, Bryton, 1943 (Box 3)
  - Barr, Stringfellow, 1940 (Box 3)
  - Barnhart, John D., 1946 (Box 3)
  - Barrett, Laura (Social Science Research Council), 1941-1942 (Box 3)
  - Bassett, Mrs. J. L., 1944 (Box 3)
  - Bassett, Michael E. R. (Box 3)
  - Bassett, W. G., 1938-1939 (Box 3)
  - Bassett Project of Publication Board, 1963 (Box 3)
  - Baxter, Stephen B. (Box 3)
  - Bay, Edna (Box 3)
  - Bayley, W. A. (Box 3)
  - Bayntun, George (Box 3)
  - Beall, Mrs. L. L., 1944 (Box 3)
  - Beatson, James A., 1950-1959 (Box 3)
  - Beck, Earl R. (Box 3)
  - Bedford County Archivist (Box 3)
  - Bers, Burton F. (Box 3)
  - Bell, J. Bowyer (Box 3)
  - Beres, Herbert, 1946-1947 (Box 3)
  - Bernard, L. L., 1939 (Box 3)
  - Berry, Lampton (Box 3)
  - Bettersworth, John Knox, 1932-1952 (Box 3a)
  - Bevington, M. M., 1955-1961 (Box 3a)
  - Bieber, Ralph, 1944 (Box 3a)
  - Biggs, Walter A., 1952 (Box 3a)
  - Bilbo, Theodore G., 1937-1939 (Box 3a)
  - Binkley, William C., 1944-1950 (Box 3a)
  - Birch, A. (Box 3a)
  - Bishop, David H., 1936-1954 (Box 3a)
  - Bisland, Louise, 1936-1937 (Box 3a)
  - Black, Forrest R. II (Box 4)
  - Blackburn, John O. (Box 4)
  - Blackburn, William Maxwell, undated (Box 4)
  - Blackwell's (Box 4)
  - Blakeley, Brian Layton (Box 4)
  - Blank and Stoller, 1938 (Box 4)
  - Blossom, Thomas (Box 4)
  - Boger, Kenneth S. (Box 4)
  - Bolich, W. Bryan, 1947-1972 (Box 4)
  - Bond, N. B., 1931 (Box 4)
  - Bond, W. F., 1932 (Box 4)
  - Bondurant, Mrs. A. L., 1941 (Box 4)
  - Boney, F. N., 1971-1972 (Box 4)
  - Borchardt, D. H. (Box 4)
  - Boyce, Benjamin (Box 4)
  - Boyce, Peter, undated (Box 4)
  - Boyd, Julian P., 1940 (Box 4)
  - Boyd, Minnie Clare, 1955 (Box 4)
  - Boyd, William Kenneth, 1938 (Box 4)
  - Bradley, Harold W., 1944 (Box 4)
  - Brady, Jane Tullia Smith, 1939 (Box 4)
  - Bradway, John S., 1950 (Box 4)
  - Braibanti, Ralph (Box 4)
  - Brandenburg, David J., 1949-1950 (Box 4)
  - Brandon, Mrs. Charles G., 1937 (Box 4)
  - Branscomb, Harvie, 1946 (Box 4)
  - Brashares, Richard A. (Box 4)
  - Bratton, Theodore D., 1936-1937 (Box 4a)
  - Bratton, Thomas and Nettle, 1933-1948 (Box 4a)
  - Bremer, R. E., 1940 (Box 4a)
  - Breedlove, Joseph Penn, 1953 (Box 4a)
  - Brice, Ashbel G. (Box 4a)
  - Brickell, H. and N., 1941-1946 (Box 4a)
  - Brinkley, W. R. (Box 4a)
  - Bristow, J. Chambers, 1949 (Box 4a)
  - British American Tobacco Co. (Box 4a)
  - British Embassy, 1940 (Box 4a)
  - British Columbia, University of, 1967 (Box 4a)
  - British Daily and Sunday Press, 1959 (Box 4a)
  - British Information services, 1959-1960 (Box 4a)
  - British Library of Information, 1938 (Box 4a)
  - British Museum (Box 4a)
  - British War Relief Society, 1940 (Box 4a)
  - Brock, J. R. (Box 4a)
  - Brock, Michael George (Box 4a)
  - Brocker, Galen (Box 4a)
  - Bromleigh, Gray, Jr., 1958-1964 (Box 4a)
  - Brookings Duke Conference on International Relations, 1949 (Box 4a)
  - Brower, A. S., 1945-1956 (Box 4a)
  - Brower, A. S., Party for, 1959 (Box 4a)
  - Brown, David (Box 4a)
  - Brown, Elizabeth H. G., 1954 (Box 4a)
  - Brown, Frances, 1962 (Box 4a)
  - Brown, Lloyd A., 1945 (Box 4a)
  - Brown, Maud M., 1929 (Box 4a)
  - Brown, Patricia, 1953 (Box 4a)
  - Brown, Truesdell S., 1940-1941 (Box 4a)
  - Brown University--Librarian, 1949-1952 (Box 4a)
  - Brown, William O., 1958 (Box 4a)
  - Brownell, William A., 1947-1958 (Box 4a)
  - Bruton, Mrs. E. M. (Box 5)
  - Bubas, Victor A. (Box 5)
  - Budd, James, 1945 (Box 5)
  - Budd, Louis J. (Box 5)
  - Bull, Mr. and Mrs. H. N., 1963 (Box 5)
  - Bulwinkle, Alfred L., 1944 (Box 5)
  - Bumgartner, Louis E. (Box 5)
  - Burger, Nash Kerr, 1932-1973 and undated, 4 folders (Box 5)
  - Burns, Sir Alan, 1962 (Box 6)
  - Burris, Craven Allen (Box 6)
  - Burton, Ann M. (Box 6)
  - Burton, Harold H., 1944 (Box 6)
  - Butts, A. B., 1941 (Box 6)
  - Butterfield, L. H., 1952 (Box 6)
  - Cain, Rob J. (Box 6)
  - Caldwell, Wallace E., 1953 (Box 6)
  - Campbell, E. S., 1941 (Box 6)
  - Campbell, William B. (Box 6)
  - Canadian Historical Association, 1961-1966 (Box 6)
  - Canadian Historical Review (Box 6)
  - Canadian Historical Society, 1962 (Box 6)
  - Canadian Learned Societies, 1963 (Box 6)
  - Canadian Newspapers (Box 6)
  - Candler, Frances G., 1943 (Box 6)
  - Capirs, Charlotte, 1943-1952 (Box 6)
  - Cappon, Lester, 1948-1956 (Box 7)
  - Carnegie Corporation, 1948 (Box 7)
  - Carnegie Institution of Washington, 1939-1941 (Box 7)
  - Carroll, E. Malcolm, 1940-1959 (Box 7)
  - Carroll, (John) Wallace (Box 7)
  - Carswell, G. H., 1940 (Box 7)
  - Carter, Clarence E., 1937-1954 (Box 7)
  - Cartter, Allan M. (Box 7)
  - Cartwright, William H., 1953-1968 (Box 7)
  - Cashman, R. I. (Box 7)
  - Caughey, John W., 1944 (Box 7)
  - Cavett, Longstreet, 1946 (Box 7)
  - Cavett, Mrs. James R., 1945 (Box 7)
  - Cavitt, John B., 1931 (Box 7)
  - Cell, John W. (Box 7)
  - Chadwick, John (Box 7)
  - Chaffin, Nora C., 1940-1956 (Box 7)
  - Chambers, Moreau B., 1936-1942 (Box 7)
  - Chapel Hill Road Fight, 1949 (Box 7)
  - Chastain, James G., Jr., 1934 (Box 7)
  - Cheshire, Leone E., 1940 (Box 7)
  - Christopher, John B., 1941 (Box 7)
  - Churchill, George M., 1940 (Box 7)
  - Citizens Travel Bureau, 1938 (Box 7a)
  - Claitor's Book Store, 1939 (Box 7a)
  - Clapham, L. B., 1942 (Box 7a)
  - Clarion-Ledger, 1941-1943 (Box 7a)
  - Clark, A. N., 1942 (Box 7a)
  - Clark, H. E., 1942 (Box 7a)
  - Clark, Manning (Box 7a)
  - Clark, Thomas D. (Box 7a)
  - Clay, Capt. A. T., 1943 (Box 7a)
  - Clay, Charles Travis, 1938 (Box 7a)
  - Clay, David M., 1945-1948 (Box 7a)
  - Clayton, Bruce L. (Box 7a)
  - Clements Library (Box 7a)
  - Clerk of Chancery Court, 1945 (Box 7a)
  - Clerk of Parliament, 1938 (Box 7a)
  - Clifton, James M., 1955-1956 (Box 7a)
  - Clingon, Courtenay (Box 7a)
  - Clonts, Forrest W., 1940 (Box 7a)
  - Clyde, Paul H., 1940-1972 (Box 8)
  - Coates, Miss W. D., 1958-1963 (Box 8)
  - Cohn, David S., 1940 (Box 8)
  - Coker, William S. (Box 8)
  - Cole, Arthur C., 1940 (Box 8)
  - Cole, John H. (Box 8)
  - Cole, R. Taylor, 1946-1972, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Coleman and Adams, 1945 (Box 8a)
  - Collector of U.S. Customs, 1958 (Box 8a)
  - Collier, P. F., and Son Corp., 1945-1951 (Box 8a)
  - Collins, Carvel, 1959 (Box 8a)
  - Columbia Broadcasting System, 1941-1945 (Box 8a)
  - Commager, Henry S., 1952 (Box 8a)
  - Community Chest, 1947 (Box 8a)
  - Conacher, J. B., 1969 (Box 8a)
  - Conference on British Studies, 1958-1964 (Box 8a)
  - Connery, Robert H., 1959 (Box 8a)
  - Conger, Thea, 1940 (Box 8a)
  - Connor, R. D, W., 1938 (Box 8a)
  - Cook, R. C., 1934 (Box 8b)
  - Cooper, John, 1942 (Box 8a)
  - Corbitt, D. L., 1950-1959 (Box 8a)
  - Cornell Law School, 1942 (Box 8a)
  - Cornwall's Old Book Shop, 1939 (Box 8a)
  - Cox, Robert C., 1947 (Box 8a)
  - Cranmer-Byng, J. L., 1960 (Box 8a)
  - Crane, Robert, 1961-1970 (Box 8a)
  - Creekmore, Hubert, 1934-1937 (Box 8a)
  - Craven, Frank, 1955-1965 (Box 8a)
  - Crawford, R.M., 1959 (Box 8a)
  - Crisp, Finlay, 1964 (Box 8a)
  - Crittenden, Christopher, 1941-1954 (Box 8b)
  - Cross, Arthur Lyon, 1935 (Box 8b)
  - Crocker, Walter Russell, 1957-1967 (Box 8b)
  - Crowe, Charles R., 1958 (Box 8b)
  - Cunningham, Noble E., Jr., 1956-1972 (Box 8b)
  - Currier, Stephen, 1963 (Box 8b)
  - Davidson College, 1941 (Box 8b)
  - Davis, Charles S., 1935-1968 (Box 8b)
  - Davies, Godfrey, 1942 (Box 8b)
  - Davis, Edwin A., 1939 (Box 8b)
  - Curtiss, John S., 1954 (Box 8b)
  - Davy, Grant, 1959-1963 (Box 8b)
  - Dale, William P., II, 1948-1966 (Box 8b)
  - Davis, Whitman, 1936-1944 (Box 8b)
  - "Darrah", 1940s? (Box 8b)
  - DeConde, Alexander, 1957-1961 (Box 8b)
  - Davenport, Rodney, 1962 (Box 8b)
  - Delaware Historical Society, 1948-1953 (Box 8b)
  - Dept. of Archives, LSU, 1939 (Box 8b)
  - Davis, Calvin, undated (Box 8b)
  - Dept. of State, Division of Research and Publication, 1939 (Box 8b)
  - Destler, Chester McArthur, 1948 (Box 8b)
  - Dictionary of American History, 1938 (Box 8b)
  - de Montluzin, Emily Lorraine, 1971-1972 (Box 8b)
  - de Vyver, Frank, 1953-1972 (Box 8b)
  - Dillon, Richard H., 1962 (Box 8b)
  - Doherty, Dr. Robert E., 1939 (Box 8b)
  - Dooley, Dennis A., 1940 (Box 8b)
  - Dornbusch, C. E., 1962 (Box 8b)
  - Doubleday and Co., 1948 (Box 8b)
  - Dowd, David, 1964-1965 (Box 8b)
  - Duke University (Box 9)
    The Duke University subseries is part of the Alphabetical Files series, and extends from box 9 through box 56. It also includes boxes 165-168, 177, and part of 178.
  - Dozier, John M., 1963-1965 (Box 8b)
  - Duke University-See also Printed Material: Duke University (Box 56)
  - Drake, W. M., 1937-1946 (Box 8b)
  - Dukes, Charles A., 1940-1960 (Box 56)
    - Academic Council:
      - Ballots, 1963 (Box 9)
      - By-Laws, 1962 (Box 9)
      - Executive Committee Minutes, 1962-1964and Aug. 31,1967 (Box 9)
      - Executive Committee Correspondence, etc., 1962-1964 (Box 9)
      - Academic Council Minutes, 1962-1966 (Box 9)
      - Academic Council Minutes, 1967-1972 (Box 10a)
      - Academic Council Correspondence (Box 10)
      - Reports, Memoranda, etc. 1962-1972 (For earlier material, see records of the University Council, predecessor of the Academic Council) (Box 10)
    - Academic Standards, 1953-1961 (Box 11)
    - African Studies: (Box 12)
      - Africa Applications and Expenditures 1957-1966 (Box 12)
      - Africa Expenditures (Manchester), 1965-1966 (Box 12)
      - Africa Grants, 1965 (Box 12)
      - Africa Instructor 1966 (Box 12)
      - Africa Session 1966 (Box 12)
      - African Committee (Old), 1962-1968 (Box 12)
      - African Committee (New), 1965-1966 (Box 12)
      - Beidelman, Thomas O., 1964-1966 (Box 12)
    - American Association of University Professors, 1942-1970 (Box 13)
    - Archives and Records Management Committee 1947, 1954-1966 (Box 14)
    - Attrition Subcommittee, 1956-1958 (Box 14)
    - By-Laws, undated (Box 15)
    - Centennial Celebration, 1938-1939 (Box 15)
    - Centennial Celebration of Teacher Education-Conference on Teacher Training, 1951-1952 (Box 15)
    - Committees, Committee on, 1963 (Box 15)
    - Communication with the Public, Committee on, 1960-1961 (Box 15)
    - Commonwealth-Studies Center: (Box 16)
      - Conference on Canada-U.S. Relations 1961 (Box 16)
      - A Decade of the Commonwealth-Conference at Bellagio, Italy, 1964 (Box 16)
      - A Decade of the Commonwealth (1966): Letters, interviews, and Drafts of Essays (Austin-Goodwin) (Box 17)
      - A Decade of the Commonwealth (1966): Drafts of Essays (Hamilton-Piper) (Box 18)
      - A Decade of the Commonwealth (1966): Drafts of Essays (Rajan-Wilson) (Box 19)
      - International Conference--Hemispheric Relations of the Caribbean and the Commonwealth, 1969-1970 (Box 19)
      - Joint Seminar 1957-1961 (Box 20)
      - Joint Seminar 1961-1963 (Box 21)
      - Joint Seminar 1963-1964 (Box 22)
      - Joint Seminar 1964-1966 (Box 23)
      - List of Selected Official Publications and Serials of the British Commonwealth in the Duke University Library,1959 (Box 23)
      - The Transfer of Institutions, 1964-1967 (Box 23)
    - Commonwealth-Studies Committee, 1955-1963 May (Box 24)
    - Commonwealth-Studies Committee, 1963 June-1965 (Box 25)
    - Commonwealth-Studies Committee 1966-1969 (Box 26)
    - Council on Instruction for Women 1941 (Box 26)
    - Courses of Instruction, Committee on 1948 (Box 26)
    - Curriculum Report 1960 (Box 26)
    - Duke Homestead, 1968 (Box 27)
    - Educational Facilities Committee 1962 (Box 27)
    - Educational Facilities Committee 1963-1964 (Box 28)
    - Educational Facilities Committee 1965-1969 (Box 29)
    - Educational Facilities Committee: Men's Athletics, 1964-1965 (Box 29)
    - Educational Facilities Committee: West Campus Dormitories, 1962-1964 (Box 29)
    - Engineering College, 1951-1969 (Box 30)
    - Faculty Club,1946, 1967 (Box 30)
    - Faculty Matters, 1947-1963 (Box 30)
    - Faculty Reorganization, Committee on 1950-1952 (Box 30)
    - Faculty--Retired, 1949-1952 (Box 30)
    - Faculty-Student Advisory System Committee 1952-1953 (Box 30)
    - Financial Aid Report, 1965 (Box 30)
    - Forestry School (See Hamilton's Writings,1949) (Box 30)
    - Freshman Advisory Council 1939 (Box 30)
    - Graduate School 1950-1962 (Box 31)
    - Historical Publications, 1959-1966 (Box 31)
    - Historical Publications: Addy, Bumgartner, Esler, Esthus, Goff, Rock, Salmond, Stark, Steele, TePaske (Box 31)
    - Honorary Degrees, 1959-1965 (Box 31)
    - History Department, 1935-1968 (Box 32)
      - Papers, 1935-1965 (Box 32)
      - Papers, 1966-1968 (Box 33)
      - Alumni Letters, 1948-1953 (Box 33)
      - Census, 1938-1958 (Box 33)
      - Course Descriptions (Box 33)
      - Course Grade Books 1930's-1970's (Box 34)
      - Course Notes (Box 35)
      - Course Schedules 1943-1946 (Box 36)
      - Examinations, 1931-1972 (Box 36)
      - Instructorship Applicants, 1961-1962 (Box 36)
      - Long-Range Planning Committee, 1958-1959 (Box 36)
      - Newsletters 1949-1968 (Box 37)
      - Newspaper Articles (Box 37)
      - Persons with History Ph.D.'s (Box 37)
      - Seminar in Teaching of History in College, 1929-1960 (Box 37)
      - Student Evaluations of Hamilton's Courses,1951-1971 and undated (Box 37)
      - Trip to Recruit Graduate Students, 1953 (Box 37)
      - Student Recommendations and Other Matters, 1946-1969 (Box 38)
    - Institutional Studies Office: Placement of Doctoral Recipients, 1959-1961 (Box 38)
    - International Studies Committee, 1963-1965 March (Box 38)
    - International Studies Committee, 1965 April-1966 (Box 39)
    - Junior English Examination, 1949 (Box 39)
    - Law School:
      - Bench and Bar Society, 1948 (Box 39)
      - Undergraduate Preparation for the Study of Law, 1949 (Box 39)
    - Library: (Box 40)
      - Acknowledgments of Gifts by Hamilton (Box 40)
      - Annual Reports, 1941/42-1967/68 (Box 40)
      - Friends of the Library, 1939-1969 (Box 40)
      - History Department Library Committee, 1945-1951 (Box 40)
      - Labor Archives, 1952 (Box 40)
      - Latin American Library Project (Box 40)
      - Library Notes, 1937-1943 (Box 40)
      - Newsletters, 1954-1961 (Box 41)
    - Library and Library Council,1934-1947 (Box 41)
    - Library and Library Council,1948-1963 (Box 42)
    - Library and Library Council,1964-1970 and undated (Box 43)
    - Library Council:
      - Charter and By-Laws, 1934-1949 (Box 43)
      - Executive Committee Minutes, 1934-1951 (Box 43)
      - Executive Committee Minutes, 1934-1960 (Box 44)
      - Council Minutes, 1934-1960 (Box 44)
      - Committee on Publications by the Library, 1946 (Box 44)
      - Human Relations Area Files, 1950 (Box 44)
      - Nominating Committee for Librarian, 1945 (Box 45)
      - Newspaper Committee, 1945-1948 (Box 45)
      - Periodicals Committee, 1946-1951 (Box 45)
    - Local Historical Resources Conference, 1953-1954 (Box 45)
    - Long Range Planning and Development Committee, 1958-1963 (Box 45)
    - Men's Interfraternity Council, 1947 (Box 46)
    - National Council (Alumni), 1948-1953 (Box 46)
    - Presidents:
      - Flowers, Robert L., 1941-1948 (Box 46)
      - Selection of President, 1948 (Box 46)
      - Edens, Hollis
        - Inauguration, 1949 (Box 46)
        - Correspondence, 1949-1960 (Box 46)
        - Resignation, 1960 (Box 46)
      - Hart, Deryl, 1960-1963 (Box 46)
      - Knight, Douglas M. (Box 47)
        - Inauguration, 1963 (Box 47)
        - Correspondence, 1962-1969 (Box 47)
        - Clippings, 1962-1968 (Box 47)
    - Press, 1938 and undated (Box 47)
    - Research Council, 1939-1961 (Box 47)
    - Seminars (University in a Changing World) (Box 48)
    - Senior Professors to Trustees, 1969 (Box 48)
    - Social Standards Committee, 1939 (Box 48)
    - South Atlantic Quarterly, 1951-1958 (Box 48)
    - Southern Studies Center, 1965 (Box 48)
    - Space Allocation Committee, 1960-1963 (Box 48)
    - Student Life and Activities, 1947-1967 (Box 48)
    - Symposia, 1963-1967 (Box 48)
    - Trinity College Historical Society, 1942-1969 (Box 49)
    - Trustee-Faculty Liaison Committee, 1960-1964 (Box 49)
    - Undergraduate Faculty Council, 1946-1969 (Box 49)
    - Undergraduate Student Counselling on Military Service Committee, 1951 (Box 49)
    - University Admissions Committee, 1962 (Box 50)
    - University Council, 1951-1960 (Box 50)
    - University Council, 1961-1962 March (Box 51)
    - University Council, 1962 April-1962 December and undated (Box 52)
    - University Council: University By-Laws, 1960-1962 (For later material, see records of the Academic Council, successor of the University Council) (Box 52)
    - University Planning Committee, 1958-1963 (Box 52)
    - University Planning Committee, 1964-1965 and undated (Box 53)
    - University Policy Advisory Committee, 1963-1964 (Box 53)
    - Woman's College: (Box 54)
      - Art Center, 1963-1967 (Box 54)
      - Board of Visitors, 1964-1965 (Box 54)
      - Committee on Dormitories, 1965-1966 (Box 54)
      - Committee on Woman's College, 1963-1967 (Box 54)
      - Library, 1941-1968 (Box 55)
      - Physical Education, 1965-1966 (Box 55)
      - Report of Dean Margaret Ball,1964 (Box 55)
      - Space for Offices, Classrooms, etc., 1960-1968 (Box 55)
      - Woman's College Question, 1961-1963 (Box 56)
    - Woman's Student Government Association, 1942-1946 (Box 56)
    - YMCA, 1942-1945 (Box 56)
  - Duly, Leslie Clement, 1960-1966 (Box 56)
  - Downs, Murray S., 1953-1970 (Box 8b)
  - Dupre, Prof. Huntley, 1941 (Box 56)
  - Duke, Bill, 1953 (Box 8b)
  - Durham, Carl T., 1939-1951 (Box 56)
  - Durham City Club, Inc., 1963-1965 (Box 56)
  - Durham County Draft Board No. 3, 1942 (Box 56)
  - Dwire, Henry R., 1940-1943 (Box 56)
  - Eades, M. R., 1941 (Box 56)
  - Easterbrook, Professor W. T., 1957-1958 (Box 56)
  - Easton, J. C., 1940 (Box 56)
  - Edwards, Everett E., 1941-1946 (Box 56)
  - Edwards, Francis, Ltd., 1938-1939 (Box 56)
  - Ellen, John C., 1942-1948 (Box 56)
  - Emerson, Mrs. E. H., 1950 (Box 56)
  - Emporium,1939 (Box 56)
  - Encyclopaedia Britannica, 1937 (Box 56)
  - England, J. Merton, 1952 (Box 56)
  - English Proficiency, undated (Box 56)
  - English-Remedial, 1947 (Box 56)
  - English Teachers Association (N.C.), 1951-1953 (Box 56)
  - Entenman, Edith, 1944 (Box 56)
  - Evans, Mary L., 1952-1954 (Box 56)
  - Evans, W. H., Jr., 1944 (Box 56)
  - Everett, Mrs. B. B., 1940 (Box 56)
  - Fant, Mrs. C. L. (Lester Glenn and Cordelia), 1930-1948 (Box 56)
  - Farley, Alice and Nancy, 1928-1945 (Box 56)
  - Farley, Robert J., 1937-1938 (Box 56)
  - Farrar and Rinehart, Publishers, 1939 (Box 56)
  - Farthing, J. D., 1968 (Box 56)
  - Feild Co-operative Association, 1938 (Box 56)
  - Fiddes, Patricia M., 1965-1966 (Box 56)
  - Fieldhouse, D. R., 1957 (Box 56)
  - Finley, Mrs. Thomas, 1944-1961 (Box 56)
  - Fitzgerald, Mrs. Fletcher P., 1938-1939 (Box 56)
  - Fletcher, F. J., 1966-1967 (Box 56)
  - Flynn, W. Paul, 1954 (Box 56)
  - Folger Library, 1960-1966 (Box 56)
  - Forbes, Allyn B., 1939-1940 (Box 56)
  - Ford Grants, 1955-1956 (Box 56)
  - Foster, T. D., 1949 (Box 56)
  - Franklin, Burt, 1945 (Box 56)
  - Fuller, F. L., Jr., 1940-1941 (Box 56)
  - Funderburk, E. C., 1958 (Box 56)
  - Gagan, David P., 1964 (Box 56)
  - Garner, Alfred W., 1945 (Box 56)
  - Gates, Paul W., 1953 (Box 56)
  - George, Walter F., 1941 (Box 56)
  - Georgia Review, 1947 (Box 56)
  - German, Paul M., 1946 (Box 56)
  - Gerschefski, Edwin, 1942 (Box 56)
  - Gibbs, Ann Margaret, 1936 (Box 56)
  - Gibson, William M., 1943-1950 (Box 56)
  - Gilbert, Katherine, 1946 (Box 56)